morning hopefully this particular works
so I sat down to write this talk I
really racked my brains to try to figure
out what the most interesting and
relevant and and useful content would be
for a lot of people who are sort of
interested in web startups when I
thought about it in those terms the
topic of my talk became fairly obvious
but then but I thought about it more and
the algorithm doesn't even seem to be
deterministic I'm not sure anyone even
knows how it works so I guess I'll
actually have to talk about stripe
instead two years ago Brian from Airbnb
spoke at our school in 2010 and the open
is talked by showing a picture of
startup school in 2008 two years
previously and that picture showed a
snapshot of the audience I picked out
one particular head he was just sitting
there an anonymous had in the audience
and I know this because I was at his
talking 2010 and so curious later he was
on stage at school and somehow tears
later Here I am and I'm sure there's at
least one person here who who'd be on
stage in in two years time and stripe
definitely isn't as far along as Airbnb
but it read Rove home the point to me
when I realized this that startups are
very unpredictable um you know Sarge
there's really hard to get your head
around I remember somebody telling me
not all that long ago that that Airbnb
was just becoming a huge success they
were making something like $10,000 a
week remember thinking man that's really
impressive
and now I have no idea what Airbnb is
actual revenue figures are today but it
wouldn't it all shock me if they're
making $10,000 an hour like what's even
like to try to build a company where
that kind of growth is possible startups
are strange for a bunch more reasons you
know they're usually kind of
counterintuitive because if they were in
counterintuitive somebody else would
probably yourself ever the problem is
already and on top of that syrups often
don't actually want don't actually want
to be all that well understood it can
actually be quite helpful to be sort of
underestimated and under comprehended
um but I think the biggest reason that
startups are hard to understand is that
so few people still get to see them up
close during those first couple orders
of magnitude and when people do tell the
stories or when the stories are told
they often tend to be kind of wrong
they're about sort of rocket ships and
frantically holding on and trying to add
more server capacity as quickly as you
can to handle the next million users
they're not about the late night
arguments and wondering if your product
could ever possibly work or trying to
figure out once you've launched your
product why it's not growing and the
thing is even the really successful
startups have this phase but that that
famous summer when Facebook moved out to
Palo Alto in 2004 most people didn't
realize this but there were other people
in the same house working in other
startups like this is the most
successful technology company started in
the 21st century and in the same house
there were people working other startup
ideas as six months after launch its it
really takes a while and so stripe is
obviously very very different to
Facebook and Airbnb and and nowhere near
as sort of far along as they are but
we've now gone through a small bit of
growth and so I want to try to describe
how it how it actually works in October
of 2009 John and I were walking home
from dinner in Potrero up in the city
and we should have been kicking around
this idea of starting an online payments
company we're really kind of fascinated
by the concept of internet payments and
all the other companies in the space
seemed like total dinosaurs and it's the
web sort of spread around the world and
more deeply into our lives through
mobile devices
it seemed kind of obvious there should
be some kind of universal payments
infrastructure of the Internet though it
should be just really easy to transact
online and John just turned to me said
you know well didn't debate about it you
know how do we just go build it probably
won't be all that hard he actually said
that it probably would be all that hard
and so I said okay sure why not
backtrack a little bit here John is my
co-founder right stripe um he's Alta my
brother and people often asked me about
how this works in practice and so for
the record starting a company with your
brother turns out to your really good
idea John is not only one of most
brilliant people I know I think he got
the highest-ever results in ireland's
university entrance examinations but
he's also someone with whom I've
literally decades of experience building
things here's an an earlier venture that
we worked on together and so it's
October 2009 we decide to work in this
online payments company we decided to
call it slash dev slash payments you
know the API should be just as
straightforward as any other node in dev
FS we're kind of okay at programming and
definitely not at naming things but
everyone else seriously have been
targeting their product it's like they
told was it a finance sector product
they were targeting is CFO's and at
business people and we thought the
internet was just moving in a completely
different direction and we decided to
target makers the people actually
building things we thought that internet
payments was a technology problem and we
wanted to build a completely new stack
for anybody transacting online so we
work nights and weekends we were both in
college at the time I was at MIT and
John was up the road at Harvard and so
we'd code together in the evenings
between problem sets and writing papers
January rolled rounds which for both of
those schools you sort of have that
month off but of course anybody who
knows Boston knows that January in
Boston is unbelievably freezing and so
we decide to go somewhere else to work
for the month we'd read a few blogs that
claim that Buenos Aires was surprisingly
a really good place to get things done
it's it's pretty cheap it's really warm
its friendly for some reason I don't
know why there was Wi-Fi everywhere
everything happens on a really late
schedule like the bars are open till
5:00 a.m. nobody has dinner until
midnight and nothing nothing starts
before noon and it's busy a city on a
program reschedule
and so you read all this and we're like
great we're good of one azari's and so
we did and we just worked non-stop in
cafes for three weeks I've still never
seen a single one of like the tourist
attractions in Buenos Aires or I presume
they exist and and then we'd like we
could all day and we'd go to dinner
eleven o'clock or something and then go
to bed
um I can't have a size isn't enough if
you want to get something done consider
going to minus R Eason
On January 9 we we got our first
production user for left / dad flex
payments I can't really say it and this
is only a few weeks after we started
working on it but we really wanted to
get production users shaping a product
as quickly as we could the user was a
friend of ours a guy called Russ Boucher
was working a company called trading
north at the time who's also actually YC
funded and funnily enough he actually
became the seventh person to work at
stripe but that's a separate story and
here's a screenshot of what debt
payments looked like at the time and
this screenshot you can see that John
and I are definitely programmers and app
designers but okay so January 9th
we now have one user and
this is a great story from the early
days of Amazon that I have a celebrated
when they got their first fire who
wasn't any of their moms and you know
Ross wasn't exactly our mom but he was a
good friend and so he definitely weren't
out of the woods just yet so he went
back to school and weakened huge work on
death payments in our spare time there
was this one cafe that I worked out of
so much they like took pity on me and
I'm still Facebook friends with a bunch
of the Bruce says that's yeah like
strife is a kind of unusual company
we're about technology but we're also
about payments and the technology side
requires good reliability and you know
clean API is an really nice product and
sort of lots of technology things we at
least hope to know something about but
the payment side requires working with
banks and dealing with credit card
companies and just generally handling a
slew of finance industry issue issues
through really had no experience with a
no idea how to handle we had a lot of
meetings where I sort of sat somebody
down and said right so payments how do
they work and you know programmers often
and this is unfortunate so looked down
at the folks who are trying to learn to
code the sort of I want to learn real to
my web startup crowd but I actually
bought a sympathy for them because we
were that but put in finance somewhere
came around when I was six months in we
moved out to Palo Alto and though we
hadn't actually yet decided to take a
leave from school we found a tiny
bungalow at just off University Ave the
living room and the kitchen became our
office it was pretty hot reading of any
air-conditioning and so John just slept
in the garden most nights and he
wouldn't allow me to post a picture of
this um and by and large we just kept on
writing code because I mean that's
mostly what starting a software company
looks like in the early days you're
either writing code or you're talking to
people who use the code or you're
probably wasting time and here's a chart
of our transaction volume over the first
six months and and that's not a
technical error if you look really
closely even see a tiny little wiggly
line at the bottom it's admittedly not
wiggling all that much around this time
though we did of our first person join
we're based in Silicon Valley home to
the best international talents from
Berlin to Beijing to Bangalore and so of
course we took
advantage of it we heard a guy called
DARAB Utley who was one of my smartest
friends from college and he grew up in a
small town called Limerick in Ireland
about two miles from her John and I grew
up we altar rates our first investment I
have a first real investment I guess YC
had obviously already invested and and
this was from from Peter teal after then
we hadn't told very many people about
dev payments and those we had told had
reacted mostly by telling us we were
crazy but of course luckily Peter teal
is crazy and so he invested and it's
been really helpful to have him on board
soon after that moved into our first
office and which looked something like
this it's actually sort of it's it's a
Ramona in University and Palo Alto just
next sort of koopa cafe that's actually
a converted house and because it was a
house it had this wonderful fireplace
they were able to light in the winter
the fireplace looks something like this
which I think may have contravenes some
fire in the workplace codes and
basically we're just working non-stop
we we actually have we became four
people around this time that the first
person fourth person was a guy named
Greg I remember
when Greg was considering joining and
dropping out of school he asked me about
our work schedule and whether or not we
worked weekends obviously we did work
weekends but it really didn't want to
make it sort of scare him off and make
it seem like he'd have to answer so I
sort of said well you know we usually
work some of the weekend we really care
about work-life balance and Greg just
cut me off and he's like great I'm
better on the same page I working all
day every day and so we knew he'd fit in
we decided to change our name I can't
even begin to list the problems that
flashed as slash payments had somehow it
turned out that not everyone immediately
got the deficit analogy nobody was
really able to get their head around the
whole slash thing and we started to get
mail with things like this
and and then there was the admittedly
pretty inconvenient fact that Amazon had
launched a product an online payments
product called Amazon dev pay and so if
Precure this wasn't going to work out
and so we spent hours brainstorming
names and we eventually came up with the
name stripe and we didn't actually think
that stripe was all that great a name
when we first came up with it but we
decide to just put a date in the
calendar and if we didn't cover the
better name by that date then we'd
secret stripe and sure enough it became
stripe and actually a few months later I
learned that this is our Apple ended up
with the name Apple it's the exact same
date thing anyway reach the end of our
first year mostly intact a bunch of Y
Combinator companies start to use stripe
and that was pretty good we're getting
some real feedback and here's another
chart this is our transaction volume
through the first year and so you can
see still kind of a ways to go we spent
January 2011 or when your anniversary in
Rio de Janeiro because January in South
America was not becoming a tradition as
anyone who's been to Rio de Janeiro
knows it's one of the most beautiful
places on earth and of course we took
full advantage of it
at this point we're still an invite-only
private beta and so there probably is
something obvious we could have done to
grow at least a little bit faster ie to
launch a friend refers to invite only
private beta as the baby blanket of
startups and I think that's about right
but the beta period was actually really
helpful to stripe um amber Paul Buchheit
saying that should start out by making
hundred people really happy rather than
many more people only a little bit happy
I mean you really took this to heart and
took advantage of the the small number
of users to sort of really focus on them
as much as we could and so really try to
figure out what they wanted it's a
forgettable not long after we launched
the first version of strife we added
pager duty so we'd all get calls from
the side was down you pretty standard
and pretty reasonable but then we
realized that any time a user gets any
kind of error like even if the site
isn't down that's actually a really bad
experience for them and we could
probably make them much happier if we
went and investigated the error and sort
of proactively reach out to them and
helped him fix it and so we changed the
code a little bit so that anytime anyone
hit any error it would send an email
that would go sort of straight the top
of everybody's inbox and would also
phone everybody and and we'd go and fix
it no matter what and I really mean that
like we would get out of bed if
necessary and we're basically never
without a laptop and the means to tether
here's a photo of one such incident
this is bragging eye we'd gone to the
cinema in Redwood City a user
encountered an error and so of course
out came our laptops and we had to go
fix it I think Greg I think Greg is here
summer actually and I think he still
feels a little bit bitter about missing
the start of the movie over this and the
movie may or may not have been Twilight
Breaking Dawn start ups are high stress
you need to unwind
we also realized that I am in with an
engineer is basically the best support
experience possible like it's really
frustrating to have to go in to file a
ticket and more like find the support
email address and then wonder does this
come to actually apply to their support
emails or if they do reply how long does
it take them or all these issues like
it's much nice we can just start sort of
directly chatting with somebody and it's
also way more productive for us because
we can then go and sort of try to figure
out what the underlying issue is rather
than having to sort of guess based on
the user's initial description so we
just opened up this this chat system on
our website where anyone can jump in and
just start asking questions and we
actually still have this today and that
was it was really good but then we
thought why stop there
isn't it really a really bad experience
when somebody asks a question and
there's nobody there to answer them and
so we thought aha pager duty and so we
hooked it up so that if you asked a
question in the Striped chat room and
there was nobody there to answer you it
would go and phone one of us after 30
seconds and so I don't think many people
know this for like for many months at
stripe if you asked a question in our
chat room and there's no one there to
answer someone will be woken up if
necessary to help you we don't do that
tonight
and so those stripe wasn't yet publicly
available to everyone we really tried to
sort of turn up the dial on our users
feedback and to force ourselves to be
extremely sensitive to what they wanted
and to what their experience was like we
our users talking to us during every
waking hour and if anything went wrong
for them they were like literally
interrupting our sleep the other thing
that kept us in beta was the fact we
weren't just building a thin software
layer and we thought that stripe should
encompass everything from the API
requests to have the money ended up in
your bank account and we wanted to be
able to define the complete experience
and we wanted to be able to do it at
scale we were sort of really influenced
by things like Amazon Web Services in
ec2 which just it's really interesting
innovation because ec2 is fantastic if
you're a small company or a startup
startup or a side project or something
like this but its scale is right through
to be a Netflix or a Zynga or indeed an
Amazon it'll work for a company of any
size and we decided that we wanted to do
that but for internet payments
infrastructure we wanted to make
something that was really easy to start
with but something would also work for
the largest companies in the world until
that meant working with really good
banks
but the problem is that banks and
startups are basically the business
equivalent of oil and water and figuring
out how to combine them is pretty hard
the best bank in the business is
probably Wells Fargo which powers some
of the largest payments companies in the
world and honestly it was pretty tough
to get them to talk to us or us even to
like return our emails and they probably
thought were some strange kind of
Nigerian scam like make money online
fast all from the comfort of your own
home so we asked a friend and investor
actually now a partner at Y Combinator
Jeff Ralston to help out Jeff had
previously been CEO of a company called
Lala an online music startup and they
had negotiated successfully with the
record labels and we thought that if you
could as a technology startup could say
it successfully with record labels you
could basically convince anyone in the
world to do anything ever and here's a
picture of Jeff on a conference call
with Wells Fargo and that's that's Dara
there on the other side and you might
wonder why is Jeff from the floor well
Jeff is on the floor because our office
was also flooded at the time and we also
had a security audit that day sometimes
turrets are just like a reality TV show
it's like negotiate with one of the
biggest banks in the world while
undergoing a security audit while
waiting through water and I don't know
the water is full of piranhas or
something but I see Jeff and a bunch of
others we eventually convinced Wells
Fargo to become one of our backends this
meant moving all of our systems to work
on top of their platform and was a
couple of weeks of honestly really
intense work we had to sort of hit a
particular deadline this is the night of
our first successful transaction this is
John after another particularly long
all-nighter and in general and I kind of
mean this seriously like this is the
unglamorous site of startups that people
do not get to see all that much like you
really want to make something work and a
lot of other people think that it's a
bad idea and it's really hard and
everything happens much much slower than
you like and you've sort of many late
night discussions like this and sort of
soul-searching debates and wondering
like this is actually a good idea or
maybe it is a good idea but it's just
too hard for us to pull off and syrups
are hard and the thing is this doesn't
actually go away this is the thing that
I didn't realize before doing a startup
I thought that sort of you have all
these doubts in the early days
then it was hard to take off and things
would get easy but no matter how
successful you will have lots of doubts
and the first American to win the trade
of France was a guy called Greg Lomond
and he has this quote I've always really
liked it doesn't get easier you just got
to go faster and it's kind of like this
foot startups like the startup might
might start going faster but it doesn't
really get easier in our case we
eventually got the pieces in place and
we got to the point for ready to launch
we launched in the 29th of September
2011 so just over a year ago at that
time stripe didn't predict had been in
production use for 19 months and and
we've been working at full time for a
year and three months
we're ten people when we launched I fail
to fit all the names in a tree and by
the end of the year here's what our
daily transaction volume looked like you
know kind of promising but the launching
is definitely not a panacea but the
signs were positive and we kept going
and over the last few months like two
and a half years in stripe is finally
started to become an overnight success
Jessica talked about how startups are
our roller coasters and there's a lot of
downs but there's also ups and the next
slide is our daily transaction volume
through to today and it looks like this
from being four people not all that long
ago stripe is now 34 people which is
actually twice as many people as are in
this picture because everything is
always behind them I start off and we
haven't got around to taking our new
group shot yet and many thousands of
companies are using stripe and a lot of
new ones go live every day and I mean
it's a bunch of well-known brands like
Foursquare and foxy and Hipmunk and the
FF and New York moment but a lot of less
well-known ones too and and they
actually tend to be sort of just as
interesting there's things like good
eggs which enables you to buy directly
from local farmers or samasource which
brings computer-based work to people
living in poverty or even stuff like the
Bedford cheese shop which is never just
selling its cheese online I guess I just
hungry you guys making these slides and
she seemed like a good idea okay um
has anyone here ever looked into the
history of container shipping sorry I
know this is a context switch from
cheese container shipping like and the
shipping container like those 40-foot
shipping containers on some level
they're the most mundane thing in the
world and we see them around all the
time but there were actually an
absolutely enormous innovation sixty
years ago before shipping containers
transportation was a massive issue with
physical goods transportation costs
often accounted for up to 25 percent of
the final cost of a physical item and
overall transportation costs and
shipping costs were like 10 percent of
the value of all the imports in the US
like think about that from a 10% that
means if your margins 20 percent just by
bringing you're good to another market
you cut your profit in half and so
unsurprisingly most manufacturing
happens are very close to where a
physical product was consumed until the
shipping container invented in the
mid-1950s
essentially eliminated the cost of
shipping physical goods it cut the cost
of loading and unloading ships by 95%
and it's now at the point 4 and actually
quoting this from a US government report
it's better to assume that moving goods
is essentially costless really and the
history here is fascinating there's a
few kind of good books about it but the
point is like this technological
breakthrough and sort of this
of friction and a particular this
abstraction of our geography it played
an enormous role in in facilitating the
rise of Singapore and South Korea and
Taiwan and Japan and China as
manufacturing hubs and we pointed really
that a technology that doesn't just
monetize itself but actually enables
newcomers can really enormous impact
like the shipping container literally
reshaped the world's economy
we sometimes subscribe we're doing with
stripe as building economic
infrastructure for the Internet it's not
very flashy but for most of human
history we've had to buy from the people
beside us but and thanks to the internet
that's no longer true we have a new way
to abstract over place anyone can now
build a global business but yeah while
the Internet has revolutionized how we
communicate and how we collaborate and
how we share we've only sort of started
to explore how that can change what we
create and how we transact and what kind
of business is possible and a lot of the
other companies whose founders are
speaking today are pretty good examples
of that it's with stripe we simply want
to turn payments into a ubiquitous
utility we want more commerce on the
Internet
but it's still really early days and
honestly most of the time we're not
thinking about these kinds of problems
we're trying figure I had to decrease
the load on DB 3 or trying to get some
particular design you know just right
and working for the 20th iteration we're
wondering if some particular product is
a good idea or having some debate you
know in Gmail that's so long we've
overflowed the Gmail thread limit and
it's now become something completely new
thread or like it's all the the
day-to-day stuff but you know it turns
out that all the high-level stuff the
the larger motivations and the bigger
ideas and the day-to-day implementation
like the debates and the tweaking and
the and the iterations both of them are
really addictive and that's why we keep
doing this thank you